Ali Zair

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests are general areas of mass communication with an extensive focus on **online misinformation**, **information processing**, **digital discourse in politics and public relations**, and **health communication**. I use traditional qualitative and quantitative methods as well as more sophisticated *computational* and *psycho-physiological methods*. Moreover, I am interested in conducting **inter-disciplinary research** in collaboration with domain experts from computer science, public health, and marketing.

EDUCATION

University of South Carolina, Columbia (UofSC)

2020 - Present Ma

May 2023 (Expected Graduation)

Ph.D. IN MASS COMMUNICATION

My doctoral dissertation is focused on assessing the interventional impact of different cues on how individuals process (mis)information on social media. I use mixed methods approach to understand how online spread of misinformation can be countered through such cues used by the mainstream social media platforms, subsequently leading to improvement and personalization of platforms' user-interfaces.

Advisor: Dr. Sei-Hill Kim

2018 – 2020 Hacettepe University, Ankara (HU)

2011 – 2015 University of the Punjab, Lahore (PU)

M.A. IN COMMUNICATION SCIENCES

B.S. IN COMMUNICATION STUDIES

PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Jun, J., Fitzpatrick, MA., Zain, A. and Zhang, N. (In Press). Have E-cigarette Risk Perception and Cessation Intent of Young Adult Users Changed During the Pandemic? *American Journal of Health Behaviors*.

AJHB '22

https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines10050735

Jun, J., Zain, A., Chen, Y., Kim, S. H. (2022). Adverse Mentions, Negative Sentiment, and Emotions in COVID-19 Vaccine Tweets and Their Association with Vaccination Uptake: Global Comparison of 192 Countries. *Vaccines*, 10(5), 735. https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines10050735

VACCINES '22

Dino Gidreta, A., Binark, M., Ozsu, G. and Zain, A. (2022). Trusts and Doubts in Africa Over Belt and Road

Initiative: A Thematic Content Analysis of Opinions in Ethiopian Twittersphere. *Etkileşim* 5(9), 12-35. DOI:

ETKILEŞIM '22

10.32739/etkilesim.2022.5.9.153

SU&M '22

Jun, J., Zhang, N., Zain, A. and Mohammadi, E. (2022). Social media discussions on the FDA's modified risk tobacco product authorization of IQOS. Substance Use and Misuse 57(3), 472-480. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2021.2019777

JAS '21

Zain, A. (2021). (Re)Production of Hindutva-Driven Populism in India: An Analysis of Bharatiya Janata Party's Political Messaging in Twittersphere. *The Journal of Asian Studies* 5(2), 179-194. DOI: 10.34189/asyam.5.2.005

Zain, A., Ozsu, G., Binark, M. and Dino Gidreta, A. (2020). China-Pakistan Economic Corridor and Technicians of Opinion in Pakistani Twittersphere: A Thematic Content Analysis. *The Journal of Asian Studies 4*(1),9-28. DOI:

JAS '20

10.34189/asyam.4.1.002

MOMENT '19

Zain, A. (2019). Rise of Modi's Tech-Populism in India. Moment Journal 6(1),199-208. DOI: 10.17572/mj2019.1.199208

PEER REVIEWED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

AEJMC '22	Zain, A. (2022, August). Moralization in Polarized Debate on COVID-19 Vaccination: Human-AI Collaborative Analys Tweets. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Detroit, First Place Moeller Student Paper Award			
AEJMC '22	Zain, A. and Long, J. (2022, August). Countering Online Misinformation: Testing Impact of State Sponsorship Labels on Message Credibility, Verification Intention and Behavior. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Detroit, MI.			
AEJMC '22	Zain, A. (2022, August). Spiral of Silence 50 Years Later: Conceptual and Empirical New Directions. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Detroit, MI.			
ICA '22	Ittefaq, M., Zain, A., and Bokhari, H. (2022, May). Opioids as Comedy: Exploring Topics, Sentiments, and Engagement in Last Week Tonight with John Oliver on YouTube. 72nd Annual International Communication Association Conference. Paris, France.			
ICA '22	Chen, Y., Long, J., Jun, J., Kim, S., Zain, A., and Piacentine, C. (2022, May). <i>Anti-intellectualism Amid the Covid-19 Pandemic: The Dynamics of Anti-Fauci Discourse on Twitter.</i> 72nd Annual International Communication Association Conference. Paris, France.			
AEJMCSEC '22	Zain, A. (2022, March). Online endorsed misinformation and climate change: using heuristic cues to assess perceived credibility of messages and sharing intentions. 47th Annual AEJMC Southeast Colloquium, Memphis, TN. Top Student Paper Award			
BDHS '22	Jun, J. and Zain, A. (2022, February). Global Comparison of COVID-19 Vaccination Sentiments and Emotions on Twitter: Findings from 192 Countries. 3rd National Big Data Health Sciences Conference. Columbia, SC			
AEJMC '21	Zain, A. (2021, August). Using Theory of Planned Behavior, and Operationalization of Political Partisanship and Belief in Misinformation to Predict Individuals' Intentions to Quit Social Media. 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, New Orleans, LA.			
AEJMC '21	Jun, J., Fitzpatrick, MA., Zhang, N., and Zain, A. (2021, August). <i>Has COVID-19 Impacted the Risk Perceptions and Cessation Intent of Youth Vapers?</i> 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, New Orleans, LA.			
AEJMC '21	Zain, A. (2021, August). Celebrity Capital and Social Movements: A Textual Analysis of Bollywood Celebrities' Tweets on 2020-21 Indian Farmers' Protest. 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, New Orleans, LA.			
AEJMC '21	Kim, S., Zain, A., and Heo, Y. (2021, August). <i>Idealized science vs. scientific skepticism in South Korea: Micro-level evidence for the two-cultures thesis.</i> 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, New Orleans, LA.			
UBSK '21	Zain, A. (2021, February). Doctrine of Hindutva and Political Discourse of India's Bharatiya Janata Party: An Analysis of 2019 Election Campaign. 1st International Social Sciences Conference, Ankara, Turkey.			
CIM '20	Ozsu, G., Zain, A., Binark, M. and Dino Gidreta, A. (2020, November). <i>Technicians of opinion in Ethiopia, Pakistan, and Turkey and their tweets about Chinese vision of alternative globalization: a comparative content analysis.</i> 17th International Symposium: Communication in the Millennium, Istanbul, Turkey. ISBN: 978-605-83703-9-5			
SENEX '19	Zain, A. (2019, November). Aging-friendly smartphones: Analysis of smartphones user-interface to assess their usability among elderly citizens. Senex: 3rd Congress of Aging Studies for Graduate Students, Antalya, Turkey.			
ETCSS M	Zain, A. and Soomro, A (2016, November). Cultural continuity and mass media: An analysis of leading online newspapers of Pakistan, 1st National Conference Emerging Trends and Challenges in Social Sciences, Multan, Pakistan			

BOOKS & BOOK CHAPTERS

Current Stage: Pre-test

Lead by: Dr. Jungmi Jun Current Stage: Data Collection

2022

Zain, A. (2020). Contact and Sanction: Use of Cricket as Diplomatic Tool by India and Pakistan. In M. Binark (Ed.), Popular Culture and Media in Asia (pp. 411-440). um:ag Publications.ISBN: 978-605-7882-42-4 2020 Zain, A. (2020). Aging Friendly Smartphones. In Y. Dede and M. Figan (Ed.), Aging in Digital Culture and Afterwards (pp. 297-314). Alternatif Bilisim Dernegi.ISBN: 978-605-80007-2-8 2020 Zain, A. and Khan, N. T. (2016). Muasharti Jamhooriat. Kettering Foundation. An Urdu translation of The Ecology of Democracy by David Mathews 2016 Under Review Publications Kim, S., Oh, S., Heo, Y., and Zain, A. (Under Review). Journalists' Conceptions of Professional Norms and Ethics in South Korea: Personal, Organizational, and Environmental Level Predictors. 2022 Zain, A. and Ciccarelli, C. (Under Review). Political Partisanship and Belief in Misinformation: Operationalizing Theory of Planned Behavior to Predict Intentions to Quit Social Media. 2022 Chen, Y., Long, J., Jun. J., Kim, S., Zain, A., and Piacentine, C. (Under Review). Anti-intellectualism Amid the Covid-19 Pandemic: The Dynamics of Anti-Fauci Discourse on Twitter. 2022 Zain, A. (Under Review). Celebrity Capital and Social Movements: A Textual Analysis of Bollywood Celebrities' Tweets on 2020-21 Indian Farmers' Protest. 2021 IN-PROGRESS PROJECTS 2022-2023 Countering Online Misinformation: A Mixed Methods Approach to Assess Efficacy of Social Media Labels. Lead by: Ali Zain Current Stage: Stimuli Development Biometric Responses and Health Outcomes of Youth Exposure to Modified Exposure Claims for Novel Tobacco Products with FDA Authorization Cues. 2021-2022 Lead by: Dr. Jungmi Jun Current Stage: Data Analysis This Ad Speaks to Me: An Investigation of Mechanisms Underlying Social Identity Relevant Advertising. 2022 Lead by: Dr. Taylor Wen Current Stage: Data Analysis Anti-social Disinformation on Social Media: The Effects of Information Sources and Message Framing. 2022 Lead by: Dr. Sei-Hill Kim

Young adults' responses to the tobacco industry's corporate social responsibility communication.

Professional Experience

2020	_	Present
2014	_	2017

University of South Carolina (UofSC) Daily Pakistan (DP)

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT/INSTRUCTOR OF RECORD CONTENT EDITOR

TEACHING INTERESTS

- · Communication Theory
- Communication Research Methods
- Digital Media & Big Data Analysis
- Health Communication

- Strategic Communication
- Public Opinion & Political Communication
- Social Media Analytics & Research
- Communication & Persuasion

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Account Planning: Mining Insights 2021 - 20222021 - 2021

Mass Communications Research

Public Relations Management 2020 - 2022

Communicating Science, Health and the Environment

FALL '21, SPRING 22

FALL '20, FALL '21

SPRING '21

FALL '20, FALL '21, SPRING '22

[Note on the teaching experience: I have taught all these courses as Instructor of Record and Teaching Assistant at the University of South Carolina. Teaching Evaluations and Teaching Philosophy are also available on request.]

AWARDS & HONORS

2022

2016

2016

2020 - 2021

First Place Moeller Student Paper Award: For presenting "Moralization in Polarized Debate on COVID-19 Vaccination: Human-AI Collaborative Analysis of Tweets" 105th annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) conference (including waiver of conference registration fee worth 200 USD)

Top Student Paper Award: For presenting "Online endorsed misinformation and climate change: using heuristic cues to assess perceived credibility of messages and sharing intentions" at 47th annual conference of AEJMC

Southeast Colloquium 2022

> University Gold Medal: For securing highest CGPA in BS Communication Studies in the class of 2015 Institute Gold Medal: For securing highest CGPA in majors during BS Communication Studies

GRANTS & SCHOLARSHIPS

2020 - 2023

Mary Caldwell Graduate Scholarship: Graduate scholarship worth 9,000 USD for the doctoral program at University of South Carolina

Junior Scholar Award: Training and research support worth 4, 500 USD awarded by South Carolina SmartState Center of Health Quality (CHQ)

2022 - 2023

ICA 2022 Michael Haley Travel Grant: To attend 72nd International Communication Association Conference in Paris, France (400 USD)

2022

ICA 2022 Political Communication Division Travel Grant: To attend 72nd International Communication Association Conference in Paris, France (400 USD)

2022

Research Grant by Hacettepe University: For the transnational study of China's Belt and Road Initiative (3, 200 USD)

2019-2020

2017-2020	Turkiye Graduate Scholarship: Fully funded scholarship for MA in Communication Sciences at Hacettepe University							
2012-2015	PU Merit Scholarship: Awarded to 5 top-ranked students at University of the Punjab							
	Professional Trainin	NGS & CERTIFICATIONS	5					
2022 – 2023	CHQ Junior Scholar Program: Extensive research taineeship offered by the SC SmartState Center for Health Quality to apply computational methods for research at the interaction of public health and social media Publication Process & Peer Review Training: Certificate program offered by the Journal of Mass Communication							
2022 – 2023	Quarterly (JMCQ) focused on formal manuscript review process training							
2021	SHARPGrads Certificate: The Skills, Habits, and Research Program for Graduate Students offered by the UofSC Digital Research Services and Research Computing Institute focused on training workshops on computing, textual analysis, programming, and visualization tools							
	Programming for Everybody: online Coursera program offered by University of Michigan focused on python							
2021	programming Citi Certificate on Human Research: Training demonstration program for social and behavioral researche							
2021	offered by Citi Program	Research: Training demons	stration program for social and	behavioral researchers				
-0-1	HubSpot Social Media Maarketing: Certificate program offered by the HubSpot Academy focused on social media							
2021	monitoring, content strategy, social engagement, creating social media policies, and demonstrating social ROI							
2024	Google Analytics: Certificate program offered by the Google Analytics Academy focused on training demonstrations and activities to test online analytical skills							
2021	demonstrations and activities to test online analytical same							
	Research Skills							
	• R/RStats	• BrandWatch	• NodeXL	• Jupyter Notebook				
	• Python	• NVivo	 Advanced Excel 	• Google Colab				
	• iMotions	• Qualtrics	• SEO	• Gephi				
	Talks/Guest Lectures							
2021	Use of new media technologi	Use of new media technologies by populist right-wing political parties in India HACETTEPE UNIVERS						
2019	Ageing-friendly smartphones to overcome digital divide in aging societies			Akdeniz University				
2017	Journalistic prospects of new	University of the Punjab						
	Service & outreach							
2022	IMIR Medical Informatics (I							
2022 2022		JMIR Medical Informatics (JMI) JMIR Formative Research (JFR)						
2022	Political Communication Di Communication (AEJMC)	Peer Reviewer Peer Reviewer						
2022	Graduate Student Interest Group, Association for Education in Journalism and Mass			Donn Dayanum				

Computational Communication Division, International Communication Association (ICA)

Communication (AEJMC)

2022

2021

Peer Reviewer

PEER REVIEWER

REFERENCES

Sei-Hill Kim KIM96@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Eleanor M. & R. Frank Mundy Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-777-7037

Jungmi Jun JUNJ@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Associate Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-576-5982

Mary Anne Fitzpatrick

FITZPATM@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Educational Foundation Distinguished Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-777-4614